Guide to the Elizabeth Hudson Collection of E. Œ. Somerville and Personal Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Other Materials Related to Somerville, 1927-1968; Series V; 0.2; (.5 box)
  - EXHIBITION CATALOGS
    - "Edith OE. Somerville, 1858-1949," catalog from an exhibition at the Neptune Gallery, 1968 Dec (Box 7, Folder 183)
    - "An Exhibition of Portraits of Great Irish Men and Women," catalog from an exhibition at the Ulster Museum, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 184)
    - "Irish Memories," catalog from an exhibition of drawings at the Ackermann Galleries, [n.y.] Apr (Box 7, Folder 185)
    - "Irish Memories," catalog from an exhibition of drawings at the home of Mr. and Mrs. Thomas Hitchcock, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 186)
  - SPIRIT WRITINGS
    - Holograph notes and a notebook of ES's spiritualist communications with Dorothy Sturges on behalf of EH, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 187-188)
      Includes: Explanatory note by EH
    - Typescript notes of spiritualist communications between Geraldine Cummins and ES after ES's death, 1949-50 (Box 7, Folder 189)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - The Commonweal, printed periodical, 1947 Oct 3 (Box 7, Folder 190)
      Includes: Barrington, Margaret. "An Irish Lady," printed article
    - Empty envelopes addressed to A. J. A. Symons and EH, probably used to send drafts of EH's Bibliography, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 191)
    - Invitation to a dinner at the University Philosophical Society, With ES as the guest of honor, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 192)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1928-68, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 193)
    - Order form for books on bibliography, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 194)
    - Photograph of ring worn by ES, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 195)
    - Sotheby & Co. (London, England). Sales catalog including manuscripts of ES, annotated by ES, 1946 Jul (Box 7, Folder 196)
    - Typescript notes on manuscript materials related to ES, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 197)
    - Unidentified envelopes, 1927-65, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 198)
    - Unidentified holograph notes, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 199)
    - Warren, Sylvia. Descriptions of horses, 1935, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 200)
- Papers Related to War and the Military, 1898-1951; Series VI; 1.45; (4 boxes)
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Letters to Elizabeth Hudson from World War I Soldiers
      - "B" General, 1917-18, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 201)
      - Bérard, Charles, 1916-18, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 202-207)
        Includes: Letter from the Major of the 114e Régiment d'artillerie lourde, a photograph of Bérard, biographical notes on Bérard, and three undated letters from EH
      - Bonnet, Maurice, 1917-38 (Box 8, Folder 208)
        Includes: Photograph of an unidentified man and woman and letter from EH dated 1919 Jul 28
      - "C" General, 1916-18 (Box 8, Folder 209)
      - "D" General, 1916 (Box 8, Folder 210)
      - Diziain, René, 1916-20, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 211-219)
        Includes: Biographical notes on Diziain
      - Dodge, A. Douglas, 1917-19 (Box 8, Folder 220)
      - "F" General, 1918, 1919 (Box 8, Folder 221)
      - Fortier, Jules, 1918-19, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 222)
      - "G" General, 1918-19 (Box 8, Folder 223)
      - Georges, Lesprit, 1917 (Box 8, Folder 224)
      - "H" General, 1918 (Box 8, Folder 225)
      - Hippolyte, Gil[?], 1918 (Box 8, Folder 226)
      - Kane, Edward A., 1918-21, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 227-229)
      - "L" General, 1929-30 (Box 9, Folder 230)
      - Lefébvre, Fleury, 1916-17, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 231-232)
        Includes: Photograph of Lefébvre, biographical notes, and eight letters from EH (1917 and undated)
      - Levasseur, Louis, 1917-19 (Box 9, Folder 233)
      - Lomas, Henry, 1919, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 234)
      - "M" General, 1917-18, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 235)
      - McDonald, J. A., 1919 (Box 9, Folder 236)
      - "P" General, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 237)
      - "R" General, 1917-19 (Box 9, Folder 238)
      - Sabatier, Marcel, 1916-44, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 239-245)
        Includes: biographical notes on Sabatier and three letters from EH ([1916?] and undated)
      - Seymour, Harry R., 1919 (Box 9, Folder 246)
      - Shough, Herbert R., 1919 (Box 9, Folder 247)
        Includes: Letter from Mrs. Charles B. Shough
      - "T" General, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 248)
      - "W" General, 1920 (Box 9, Folder 249)
      - Unidentified soldiers, 1916-18, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 250)
      - Unidentified envelopes, 1917-18 (Box 9, Folder 251)
      - 2 folders originally containing the letters, with illustrated cover and the words "Mes Lettres du Front, 1914-1915", ca. 1915 (Box 9, Folder 252-253)
    - Other Letters to Elizabeth Hudson
      - American Association for Assistance to French Artists, 1944 Nov 29 (Box 10, Folder 254)
        Includes: Catalogs for an exhibition of European paintings at the College of Wooster, and an exhibition of paintings by Jacques Maroger at Wildenstein and Company
      - American Relief Clearing House, 1916, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 255)
        Includes: Letter from the American Relief Clearing House to Dr. Paboeuf
      - Atlantic Monthly, 1916 Sep 8 (Box 10, Folder 256)
        Includes: Carbon typescript copy of a letter by René Diziain
      - Commission for Relief in Belgium, 1916 Jan 15 (Box 10, Folder 257)
      - Diziain, Marcelle, 1916 Aug 28 (Box 10, Folder 258)
      - Erhel, Annette, 1919 Jul 24 (Box 10, Folder 259)
      - Foissey, Suzanne[?], 1916-17 (Box 10, Folder 260)
      - French Relief Fund, 1944 Jan 21 (Box 10, Folder 261)
      - Fuller, Charles, 1923 Jul 30 (Box 10, Folder 262)
        Includes: Letter from Roger Armory to Fuller
      - Ingold, Augustine, 1916-19, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 263-266)
        Includes: Letter from the Comité Franco-américain pour la protection des infants de la frontière
      - Johnson, Albin E.
        See: Speeches, Box 11, folders 304-305
      - Joseph, Flora, 1917 Jan 18 (Box 10, Folder 267)
      - Keats-Shelley Association of America, 1949 Apr 24 (Box 10, Folder 268)
      - Mourand, M., 1918, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 269)
      - Musée de la coopération franco- américaine, 1950 May 19 (Box 10, Folder 270)
        Includes: Note from Elizabeth Creevey Hamm, and a pamphlet about the museum
      - National Gallery of Art (U.S.), 1945 Mar 27 (Box 10, Folder 271)
      - Newell, Harriett, 1918 Dec 23 (Box 10, Folder 272)
      - President's War Relief Control Board, 1945 Mar 26 (Box 10, Folder 273)
      - Réquin, Edouard, 1940, 1948 (Box 10, Folder 274)
      - Scott, E., [n.y.] Jan 21 (Box 10, Folder 275)
      - Simmons, Ronald, 1916 May 11 (Box 10, Folder 276)
      - Verquière, Marthe, 1916-19 (Box 10, Folder 277)
      - Volunteer Nurses Society, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 278)
      - Wharton, Francis, 1916 Sep 17 (Box 10, Folder 279)
      - ----, Sybil, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 280)
      - Transcript of a letter from an unidentified woman from Lorraine describing her experience in World War I, 1916 May (Box 10, Folder 281)
      - Unidentified, 1918, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 282)
        Includes: Two letters from EH (1918 and undated)
    - Third-Party Letters
      - Bureau féministe[?] to Mme Girardet, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 283)
      - Flichy, Mme to "Madame et Monsieur le Sénateur Dervey[?]. Photocopy, 1945 Jan 1 (Box 10, Folder 284)
      - Unidentified to Henry Lomas, 1918 Dec 6 (Box 10, Folder 285)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Bérard, Charles[?], n.d. (Box 11, Folder 286)
    - Boy in uniform, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 287)
    - Ingold, Augustine, [1917?] (Box 11, Folder 288)
    - Neal, Tim, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 289)
    - Residents of the Sanatorium de la Jonchère[?], including Augustine Ingold, [1917?] (Box 11, Folder 290)
    - Soldier and woman, 1916 Sep (Box 11, Folder 291)
    - Soldier in hospital, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 292)
    - Two young girls, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 293)
    - Woman and young girl, 1916 Sep (Box 11, Folder 294)
    - Photograph album from World War I, ca. 1912-17 (Box 11, Folder 295)
      Includes: Photographs taken mostly in France, including pictures of Mrs. [Agnes?] Baden-Powell, Charles Bérard, Mrs. Robert Woods Bliss, Sir Paul Harvey, Augustine Ingold, Augusto Floriano Jaccaci, John J. Pershing, Janet Scudder, Ruth Stillman, Countess Pierre de Viel-Castel, children under the protection of the Comité franco- américain pour la protection des enfants de la frontière, soldiers, nurses, military hospital wards, buildings and landscapes
    - Scrapbook with photographs from World War I compiled by Dorothy Sturges, 1917-19
      Includes: 2 passports of Sturges, a report on Le bien-être du blessé (Woman's Motor Unit), postcards and photographs of members of the motor unit, Col. Ronnie Hadon, C. C. Haig, Ruth Stillman, soldiers, military hospital wards, Paris landmarks and destruction caused by bombings, and letters to Sturges from the American Ambulance Field Service, the Bar Harbor War Relief Association, Madeleine d'Audigne[?], Madeleine du Luart[?], and from d'Audigne to Howard Sturges
  - SCRAPBOOKS AND CLIPPINGS
    - Newspaper clippings, 1918-49 (Box 11, Folder 296)
    - Scrapbook of military-related clippings, volume 1, 1898
      Includes: Letter from the United States Navy, Bureau of Navigation to Robert Hudson, 23 September 1876
    - Scrapbook of military-related clippings, volume 2, 1898
    - "War Clippings, Paris: 1916-1918", 1916-18
    - Scrapbook of clippings, memorabilia, letters and printed materials, 1916-18
    - Scrapbook of clippings, 1927-44
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Speeches and Writings
      - Davenport, W. S. "Food for Thought, Food for France: An Informal Appeal by the Coordinating Council of French Relief Societies," typescript, 1942 (Box 11, Folder 297-298)
      - "France Speaks to America: Letters from a Frenchwoman to the International Division of the National Broadcasting Company," printed version, 1941 (Box 11, Folder 298a)
      - Lamont, Thomas W. "Petty Anglo-American Differences to be Avoided," reprint of a letter from The New York Times, 1943 Feb 14 (Box 11, Folder 299)
      - Morgan, Charles. "Address by the English Authors Charles Morgan, Pot au Feu Luncheon, Coordinating Council of French Relief Societies, Inc.," printed version, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 300)
      - Morgan, Charles. "France Alive," reprinted from The Atlantic Monthly, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 301)
      - Phillips, Duncan. "The Arts in Wartime," address to the American Association of Museums, printed version, 1942 May 19 (Box 11, Folder 302)
      - Rousseau, Jean Jacques. "France Will Live Again," clipping of printed version, 1940 Jun 29 (Box 11, Folder 303)
      - Speeches reproduced by the Publicity Department, Coordinating Council of French Relief Societies, typescript carbons, 1941-50 (Box 11, Folder 304-305)
        Includes: Speeches by Charles Boyer, John Erskine, Julien Green, Hans Habe, Albin E. Johnson, Antoine de Saint-Exupéry, and Henry J. Taylor
    - Printed Materials
      - Allied Relief Fund. Anthology of articles in support of the Fund, 1940 (Box 11, Folder 306)
        Includes: Letters to EH from J. Reguin (copy), Winthrop W. Aldrich (copy) and an unidentified correspondent (original)
      - American Relief for France. Program for the first annual meeting, 1945 Mar 29 (Box 11, Folder 307)
      - "Benefit Exhibition for the American Field Service: American Provincial Paintings," catalog from an exhibition at the Whitney Museum of American Art, 1942 (Box 11, Folder 308)
      - British Information Services. As Hitler Sowed ... So Shall Hitler Reap!, [1942?] (Box 11, Folder 309)
      - Centre Social. Program for meeting, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 310)
      - Coordinating Council of French Relief Societies. Annual reports, 1941-44 (Box 11, Folder 311)
      - Coordinating Council of French Relief Societies. Le merveilleux voyage de la goutte de vitamine, [1942] (Box 11, Folder 312)
        Introduction by André Maurois
      - "From Paris to the Sea Down the River Seine," catalog from an exhibition at Wildenstein and Company, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 313)
      - Gréban, Arnoul. Le Vray mistère de la passion, program for a production directed by Pierre Aldebert, 1951 (Box 11, Folder 314)
      - Lockwood, Preston and Lincoln Eyre. Program for a play entitled Sham, 1914 (Box 11, Folder 315)
        Includes: Ink drawing of a man's head
      - Service d'entre'aide familiale[?]. "Les personnes déplacées", 1949 (Box 11, Folder 316)
      - Théâtre national de l'opéra-comique. "Matinée au bénéfice de l'armoire lorraine," theater program, 1916 May 17
      - Printed memorabilia, 1940-47, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 317)
    - Other Materials
      - "Diplome de membre bienfaiteur" of the Association nationale des médailles de la résistance, sent to Hudson, 1951 Jan 15 (Box 11, Folder 318)
      - Invitation to the "Cérémonie d'inauguration de l'avenue du Président-Wilson", 1918 (Box 11, Folder 319)
      - Invitations and programs for concerts, exhibitions, plays and other events to benefit war relief efforts, 1942-50, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 320-321)
      - Membership card from "France Forever," signed by Hudson, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 322)
      - "Memorandum: E. Hudson from Mr. Brunot," typescript. Regarding funding for relief efforts, 1945 Feb 19 (Box 11, Folder 323)
      - Ordre de réquisition (for animals and vehicles) subdivision de région de Melun, commune de Barbizon
      - Ribbon from a uniform[?], n.d. (Box 11, Folder 324)
      - Travel permits for Hudson, 1916-18 (Box 11, Folder 325)
      - Other papers, 1938-45, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 326)
- Oversize, 5.8; (8 boxes)
  - "Chez Pasteur," reproduction of a drawing (in Series III), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 327)
  - Child, reproduction of a drawing (in Series III), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 328)
  - Hunt scene, pencil, with an ink drawing of a child on horseback on verso (in Series III), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 329)
  - Hunt scene, reproduction (in Series III), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 330)
  - Man, reproduction of a drawing (in Series III), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 331)
  - Man and tailor[?], reproduction of a drawing (in Series III) (Box 12, Folder 332)
  - Man in robe, reproduction of a drawing (in Series III), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 333)
  - Man with hat and umbrella, reproduction of a drawing (in Series III) (Box 12, Folder 334)
  - "Strayaways: At the River's Edge," gouache painting (in Series III), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 335)
  - "They Dropped Down out of Sight," watercolor (in Series III), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 336)
  - Woman[?], reproduction of a drawing (in Series III), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 337)
  - Woman with child, reproduction of a drawing (in Series III), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 338)
  - In library with dog (in Series IV), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 339)
  - Signing a book (in Series IV), [1947-48?] (Box 12, Folder 340)
  - "The West Carberry Hounds" (in Series IV), 1903 (Box 12, Folder 341)
  - Théatre national de l'opéra-comique. "Matinée au bénéfice de l'armoire lorraine" (in Series VI), 1916 May 17 (Box 12, Folder 342)
  - Scrapbook with drawings and watercolors (in Series III) (Box 13, Folder 343)
  - Scrapbook with photographs from World War I compiled by Dorothy Sturges (in Series VI), 1917-19 (Box 14, Folder 344)
  - Scrapbook of military-related clippings, volume 1 (in Series VI), 1898 (Box 15, Folder 345)
  - Scrapbook of military-related clippings, volume 2 (in Series VI), 1898 (Box 16, Folder 346)
  - "War Clippings, Paris: 1916-1918" (in Series VI), 1916-18 (Box 17, Folder 347)
  - Scrapbook of clippings, memorabilia, letters and printed materials (in Series VI), 1916-18 (Box 18, Folder 348)
  - Scrapbook of clippings (in Series VI), 1927-44 (Box 19, Folder 349)
  - Smith, Harry Worcester. Galley proofs (in Series II), n.d. (Box bsd, folder 350)
  - Bibliography. Holograph draft page (in Series II), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 380)
  - Ordre de réquisition (for animals and vehicles) subdivision de région de Melun, commune de Barbizon (in Series VI) (Box bsd, folder 381)
- Restricted Fragile, 0.3; (2 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folders 1-23 (Box 20, Folder 351)
  - Box 2, folders 24-54 (Box 20, Folder 352)
  - Box 4, folder 55 (Box 20, Folder 353)
  - Box 4, folders 63-64 (Box 20, Folder 354)
  - Box 4, folders 89-90 (Box 20, Folder 355)
  - Box 4, folder 102 (Box 20, Folder 356)
  - Box 4, folder 110 (Box 20, Folder 357)
  - Box 7, folder 193 (Box 20, Folder 358)
  - Box 8, folder 203 (Box 20, Folder 359)
  - Box 8, folder 205 (Box 20, Folder 360)
  - Box 8, folder 212 (Box 20, Folder 361)
  - Box 8, folder 223 (Box 20, Folder 362)
  - Box 8, folder 227 (Box 20, Folder 363)
  - Box 9, folder 236 (Box 20, Folder 364)
  - Box 9, folder 237 (Box 20, Folder 365)
  - Box 9, folder 239 (Box 20, Folder 366)
  - Box 9, folder 240 (Box 20, Folder 367)
  - Box 9, folder 241 (Box 20, Folder 368)
  - Box 9, folder 242 (Box 20, Folder 369)
  - Box 9, folder 245 (Box 20, Folder 370)
  - Box 9, folder 247 (Box 20, Folder 371)
  - Box 9, folder 248 (Box 20, Folder 372)
  - Box 10, folder 255 (Box 20, Folder 373)
  - Box 10, folder 264 (Box 20, Folder 374)
  - Box 10, folder 265 (Box 20, Folder 375)
  - Box 17, folder 347 (Box 20, Folder 376)
  - Box 18, folder 348 (Box 20, Folder 377)
  - Box 19, folder 349 (Box 20, Folder 378)
  - Box 7, folder 195 (Box 21 (Art), Folder 379)